let's assume that the square root of 2
is rational so that the square root of 2
equals A over B with A and B integers
this means 2B squared equals a squared
or B squared plus b squared equals a
squared so that there exists an
isosceles right triangle with a side
length of b and a hypotenuse of a we can
swing the side length over to the
hypotenuse like this and create a
subtriangle using the construction shown
we can determine that this subtriangle
is also an isosceles right triangle the
side lengths of this new isosceles right
triangle are a minus B and the
hypotenuse is 2b minus a but now we can
use this new right isosceles triangle as
proof that two copies of a minus B
squared is equal to the quantity 2B
minus a squared but as we saw
geometrically and can verify
analytically two B minus a is a positive
integer less than a and a minus B is a
positive integer less than b so we have
found two smaller positive integers
satisfying the same equation As A and B
we can repeat this process indefinitely
producing a geometric infinite Descent
of positive integers which is a
contradiction so the square root of 2 is
irrational